let's look at specifically for live
hacking events so you know you mentioned
that you're focusing on high in critical
bugs and on in life hacking events you
don't get to pick your target right
which I I understand you're normally
pretty picky about because you have a
specific set of um of uh a very
particular set of skills uh that I was
gonna say if you want yeah exactly
okay
[Music]
[Applause]
what's up y'all we've got an excellent
episode for you today our guest is Alex
Chapman a bug Bounty Hunter renowned for
his critical vulnerabilities at live
hacking events and his extremely
extremely detailed reports
um we talked to him about everything
ranging from his red teaming experience
to how to be a full-time Buck Bounty
Hunter to how to find these crazy bones
and I think you're really going to enjoy
the episode but before we dive in I want
to remind you to head over to
ctbb.show and drop your email there
we're trying to grow that newsletter so
that we can stay in touch with you all
and so that you don't miss an episode
without further Ado Alex Chapman Alex
thanks for coming on the Pod dude
hey how are you doing pretty great dude
um this is gonna be a really cool
episode I think I've I've uh admired
your hacking from afar and from a close
uh at a at a bug Collision in January
um and so I'm really I'm excited this
time to pick your brain and kind of kind
of uh get some of those techniques out
of you
um I was hoping we could start today a
little bit with a little bit of your
infosec history and kind of talk to us
about how the hacker that is now ajx
Chapman has evolved to where he is today
yeah sure so uh I guess I'm a bit of an
old-timer uh certainly in the in the bug
Bandy crowd
um I've been doing kind of in
professional security for I guess must
be at least 16 years by now wow
um kind of starting straight out of
University professionally but interest
from when I was about what 12 13 as soon
as I could that's the age of the program
yeah as soon as I could learn the
program I kind of wanted to know how to
break things
and there wasn't as much information
around back then so um could have had to
scrape pieces together different here
and there and then
and decided to be a good idea to a
community science degree as you do uh I
hated it absolutely hated it yep
relatable it found out uh towards the
end of my degree yeah relatable for sure
um but then at one point we had a guest
lecture uh from somebody who worked for
one of the big four
um who was a pen tester I was like well
you can actually get paid to do this
sort of thing so that was from then on
that was my goal uh straight at the
University was into big four because I
know they did pen testing right now when
you say big four is that you're talking
about big four accounting firms is that
what you're going to talk about yeah
okay and I went to work for Deloitte
okay
in there specifically in their security
team and was doing pen testing from then
on so did about a decade of pen testing
three years of delight moved to a
smaller consultancy
and that's where I picked up kind of red
teaming and security research
uh knew nothing about bug Bounty at this
point so this was going back to you know
maybe 2016 2017. okay all right
um and then went to work for Yahoo
nice man I feel like a lot of a lot of
good hackers kind of go through Yahoo at
some point I don't know if it's just
like the time period of like you know
Yahoo was a big name earlier on in the
in the buck Bounty scene or in the pen
testing but
um you know I feel like I I see so many
people that have have gone through there
so I've got a couple questions for you
you mentioned that you started
programming early on
um you know was that out of it but you
didn't really get introduced to hacking
until later is that right or were you
studying programming that whole time or
was there a little bit of hacking in the
youth as well certainly a little bit of
hacking yeah kind of looking at war
games and uh oh sure sure it kind of
crap maze Uh crap me.d used to exist oh
yeah pretty sure that's been dead
yeah I don't know if that's still a
thing so
so kind of interesting a lot of reverse
engineering
um
specifically on on crackney so kind of a
legal outlet for trying to learn these
skills gotcha so so it was in college
where you were introduced to being able
to do this as a job but that's what
you're saying yeah okay yeah so I
never in kind of a million years when I
was in my early teens I thought I could
get could get paid to do this and then
just had this Epiphany moment
I can do this yeah
yeah so that was my my mission from then
on yeah dude that's awesome that's so
cool I I I I I sort of remember I
remember that moment for me as well
being like wow you know this is actually
a career path that I can go down which
is really cool because at the same you
know I I started when I was young as
well at 12 or 13 and I kind of went down
the black hat route for a while and I
was like but then I sort of caught a
conscience you know I was like oh
actually this is really damaging systems
that I'm that I'm working on trying to
cover my tracks because I wasn't
necessarily good enough to really do a
good job of covering my tracks so my my
you know my track coverings was you know
rm-rf slash you know
um and so uh uh you know that that's
kind of when I I pivoted off and and and
then you know coming into that
realization that it can actually be a
career man what what a what a
mind-boggling thing so so you mentioned
you know you were in CS but you weren't
you weren't loving that why what what is
your opinion on you know should aspire
hackers go and get a degree versus going
you know training themselves or going
through a boot camp or what
I think
my personal opinion from kind of where
we are now in 20 2023 is yeah I wouldn't
bother yeah I would
apply yourself
uh learns program I think all hackers
should know how to program at least
basically I know that's a bit of a
controversial um opinion in some circles
yep but but my view on it is you
shouldn't have had a program
um
or at least should be interested in
learning how to program sure let's say
let's say about that and just apply
yourself blog a lot blog about
everything you can so I actually used to
do used to do hiring
um and that would be the first thing I
would do if I see any past screening I
would look the person up on Twitter try
and find their blog and see what they
were interested in yeah
um and people who didn't have blogs
would actually be in I would have I know
I'd have to grow them a lot more in an
interview strong workout what their
passion is and what they're interested
in
um and again you can make money in in
bug Bounty you're not going to start out
and make the big bucks but you can get
by and you can again build up a uh an
effective CV saying Yep this company by
this uh this company by this bug and um
to me that's much more impressive these
days than somebody who came out of a
degree spending all their money to get a
paper who actually has next to no real
world experience yeah yeah I found that
to be very true I also dropped out of
college
um and like Carl I mean when I went into
college I was kind of doing some hacking
adjacent stuff like stuff that I think
now would be considered under the realm
of like bug Benny slash General infosec
hacking and I think that precursor
knowledge really helped me find the path
that I was looking for
um I had already been very interested in
like programming and computers and that
kind of stuff and so once I'd seen like
this was a route that could be taken and
it was like profitable and it was like
very interesting and it was very in line
with the stuff that I was already doing
and already found a lot of enjoyment
with it just seemed like a very natural
progression
um I'm curious like how far you sort of
like deviated from what you would
consider like what you were already
doing to Pivot into bug Bounty or was it
kind of that same natural progression
so going from pen testing and red taming
to that Bounty yeah yeah
so yeah I mean it's actually
going from more of an audit um pen test
side of side of things to bug Bounty is
a huge world of difference
um
like when in the kind of audit space
with security you're reporting
absolutely everything and looking for
absolutely everything
um so you're reporting SSL ciphers and
all the stuff that nobody cares about
has no real world impact but if you
don't report it
and the client kind of finds out about
it you can get into real trouble
um and so that's the kind of Soul
destroying end of pen testing
um but then on the red team side
I actually got a lot more experience
that would be more relatable to bug
Bounty
um and that's kind of actually trying to
find and properly exploit bugs in Anger
um see how far you can get with them and
what you can actually do with it so the
book's no longer theoretical or or
something popped up on a scanner you
know 100 that it's there and it can be
exploited for this sort of impact
um and that I think was a big learning
point for me was actually
not just CVSs impact but real world
impact yeah
so your your scanner says this is a 7.2
so it's obviously high but
what does that actually give you access
to does the business care about this
thing it was actually a third-party bit
of software that or third-party hosted
thing that means nothing
yeah and it's it's things like that if
you can kind of start to bring that um
experience into the into the bug bandage
side of things you'll find you get a lot
further as well yeah oh yeah did you
find that your time at companies were
like really helpful for figuring out
that sort of security impact because
this is something that we've talked
about a lot it's like cbss versus like
direct impact and understanding like
security model of a company and instead
of framing your bugs so that you have
like a 9.0 CVSs like that you know that
that's good and stuff but it really
matters more like what's the actual
impact how does this affect the company
how can you frame this so that the
company
sees the impact the same way that you do
and do you think that like your time at
companies and all the red team and stuff
really helped with that
yeah huge uh and that's
also I guess on the report report
writing side of things as well because
like red team we used to write kind of
96 150
um page reports wow um so
coming like when I first started doing
bug Bounty I would probably take four
hours of reached report I was writing oh
wow and that would be some basic xss
reports would take me several hours to
write so it's going into that level of
detail okay that was Overkill that's um
kind of there's still uh kind of Douglas
day working with them quite a lot and he
still takes a piss out of me for a rat
how how much I write in the reports and
how long it takes me to write a report
it's really I still like to get that
yeah it's funny because I will I used to
do like the same thing where I would go
very very in-depth I would give them
like a full explanation of like how does
this work what is this doing in the back
end and at a certain point I realized I
was like wait a second I'm just I'm
explaining to these Engineers how their
own systems work they don't really need
to know like for me this is satisfying
but for them it's like okay Skip Skip
Skip Skip oh there's the vulnerability
yeah and that's how I fix it I think I
think also for us as hackers
it's it's a fun narrative to convey you
know like you know I I found especially
on reports that I'm really proud of I'll
go above and beyond on on the you know
or at least on the bugs that I'm really
proud of I I go above and beyond on the
report because I'm like I want you to
understand what a masterpiece this is
like you know 100 uh it's yeah it's when
you get the reaction from the program
team being like wow yeah
yeah and and I bet I bet I bet you get
that a lot Alex because
um you know it does certainly happen
yeah yeah and and the fact that you
acknowledge it definitely means that it
happens a lot um you know because I've
been privy to some of the reports that
you've you've um you've found
specifically at the GitHub event
um last year just what a phenomenal
performance that was
um so that was
yeah but that was a great day wasn't it
yes that was a good day for me I believe
it man I believe it um so I'll talk a
little bit more about that later but I
wanted to come back to what you said
earlier about
um you know hackers should should be
able to program or should have an
interest in learning programming or
should have an interest in programming
um could you speak to a little bit about
how that uh just speak to that for our
listeners and also
um how how that integrates with your
style of hacking which is different than
most others I believe
yeah and that's that's a really good um
good question I was reflecting on this a
little bit earlier um
I spend
a significant portion of my time hacking
in an IDE
um I'll be pulling open source repos
down looking through the code reading
the code trying to find
issues and learn basically how a module
works or how this server works that
they're doing how the protocol works
that they're they're communicating with
right
um without being a program that would be
next to Impossible right and that's very
specific to my my style of hunting but
if you really want to in my opinion if
you really want to be able to understand
the bug you need to know how
how it was implemented what
assumptions a programmer would have made
to to introduce that bird
and
ideally how to fix it so if you know if
you know those three things you can
really Hammer home what a bug is and
um
and start to understand where you might
find it in other places as well it's all
very well kind of spraying payloads all
over a website but if you don't really
understand what's going on in the back
end and what's happening to those
payloads then
what's the point yeah yeah blindly
throwing doubts yeah that's a really
good point I was actually just talking
with
um one of my buddies who's just starting
to like get into bug Bounty and and
security and that kind of stuff and he
was going through the portswiger Web
Academy and he was telling me today that
like he's now at a point where he can if
he looks at a vulnerability he can like
80 of the time figure out what's going
on just by like sussing it out and like
doing a little fiddling with it and I
think that is so key to really making
progress in bug Bounty and hacking as a
whole but especially bug Bounty just
because it takes that level of
understanding of like what's actually
going wrong here how does this bug
interact with other systems what are the
different possibilities for me to move
laterally or vertically within this
vulnerability to escalate it or to do
XYZ and if you don't have that then it's
really just like throwing darts like
blindly at the wall and just like seeing
what sticks and just like hoping for the
best
yeah yeah I'll I'll speak I'll speak
briefly to our audience here as well
like this is another great example of
something that we talk about really
often which is
um you know you don't have to know
programming to hack but if you do know
programming you will find substantially
better bugs because you'll understand at
a deeper level what is happening and
what
um you know you'll be able to understand
the exploits that are occurring and
you'll be able to go for things that are
a little bit deeper most of the bugs
that Alex submits
um statistically even are are between
high and crit right and on the crit side
of of hot you know between high and crit
looking from his hacker One impact right
he's he's got a uh what is it 32.7
um impact on on hacker one which is
phenomenal
um and and so uh you know
this is just to just to be clear you
know we we don't we won't say that you
have to know how to program to hack but
if you if you do you will gain a much
greater ability to find critical bugs so
that's that's a great takeaway
um and um Alex bringing it back around
to your your sort of personal infosec
history you you worked at Yahoo oath
slash whatever the heck they want to
call it Verizon media you know yeah it
was it was an interesting time yeah
could you could you speak to a little
bit about that experience what were you
what were you doing there and what kind
of things did you learn
so yeah so I was on their internal red
team there
um
so that was we were kind of every month
or so be given a
an objective
and more often than not it would be try
and get access to the ceso's email and
show how we could do that with with
internal knowledge but we used to have a
with the with issues that
um kind of Yahoo and have had previously
it was there was an assumption
internally that
um internal access would be relatively
easy to obtain from an attacker's
perspective so we would kind of go from
that
um that position of being an attacker
with internal access and see what we
could do in the internal Network and
then obviously work with the various
teams to to get that fixed and and see
what other kind of defense and depth we
could we could help to uh to implement
that so you mentioned that how much of
you go ahead I'm sorry yeah so you
mentioned that a lot of the hacking that
you do is like in an IDE it's looking at
source code it's looking at how stuff
works
um has that always kind of been the case
for you just based on your background or
did you sort of pivot into that style of
hacking after doing a lot of you know
Black Box testing and all that kind of
stuff and just sort of figuring out that
this was what you liked the most or this
was what worked the best for you
yes I mean that's always been my area of
interest
um and actually kind of going even lower
down the stack into reverse engineering
and and debugging
um
and kind of binary exploitation as well
that was always my first kind of my
first infosec love uh as it were
but there was very little opportunity to
do that whilst doing kind of the audit
stuff and testing that I started out
doing
um so I remember for a couple of months
I'd be sitting in a data center with no
internet connectivity running nmap
against a billion and One servers oh man
um but I used that time to kind of read
off my main pages in in Linux and stats
program or in Tinker more
um and then it was like okay so what
have I got accessible to me I've got in
that okay so let's learn everything I
can about nmap and how it works what
it's doing and
um so it's I guess it's sort of the the
interest
um if something picks my interest on
Rabbit Hole down there and we'll just
stay there for months if I can that's so
funny I do the same thing when I'm like
whenever I'm in like a situation where I
don't have many options for what I could
be doing I think a great example is when
I'm sitting on a plane I'll start to do
things that I don't normally do so I'll
like read a book or I'll like or like
start to just like read through Man
pages or something like like I'll just
do like things that are like you know
they consume time but it's not
necessarily the most interesting thing
because I'm in this restricted sort of
environment and I feel like that's like
the perfect intersection of like
interest and opportunity breeds you know
knowledge or information or however you
want to you want to build that equation
yeah yeah God forbid you pay that 12.99
for the internet on the flight so that
you can answer emails or write tweets or
whatever on the eight hour flight yeah
exactly yeah I mean I remember quite
vividly so literally sitting in a data
center no internet access and the
particular customers working for
wanted us to leave our hard drives
um when we were done with the job and it
was kind of a four-week job and I was
like well
what am I going to do with my time
because it was literally scamming
um so I was like well
I enjoy programming so I'll just program
something and it was actually quite
liberating writing this rather than this
whole thing knowing it was going to get
thrown in the bin in a couple weeks time
and I couldn't take it with me ah nice
um and that that was that was
programming purely for the for the joy
and and the challenge
wow yeah that's awesome man that that is
how that is how growth happens you know
when you're when you're doing it for
like you're saying for the joy for of
programming for the passion of it
um but so you know this was in going
back to your your experience at Yahoo
North this is a this is a red team
um sort of role and as I understand well
my personal experience so anecdotally is
that when I was doing internal pen tests
I wasn't doing a lot of which is
different than red team but you know uh
correlated in some way
um I wasn't doing a lot of exploitation
or exploit development I was doing a lot
of pivoting around in the internal
Network I was doing a lot of escalating
of privileges inside the network in
order to weave my way through right
um so I'm wondering you know how
different that was at Yahoo internal red
team
um or if that skill set was developed
elsewhere
yeah so it was pretty similar in terms
of the pivoting and you kind of spend
probably 70 of your time on post
exploitation right
um
and that that was always the kind of
prove what you can do you
you've exploited the system now prove
what you can do with that right
um but there was the kind of 30 of
initial initial access which was
pretty pretty fun exploitation um
I remember I think
I'm sure it's fine to say this
um my my first week there I wasn't set
up properly and was just given the
standard laptop
um
so no no more privileges than anybody
else would have and by the end of the
week I had a remote code execution on
Yahoo laptops oh yeah well that's
another one of those scenarios where
you've got like limited you know limited
scenarios and you just kind of got to
work within your environment which is
such a hacker mentality thing in general
as well because our whole our whole job
is to take you know that that data
center with no internet that laptop you
know that that uh injection point where
you can't use special characters and
figure out a way to to break out of
those constraints and and get access to
you know greater privileges so I think
you know I'm sure it was applicable in
so many ways but even just from a
mentality perspective that'll help you
grow as a hacker and and build that sort
of mental resiliency you need to be able
to push through almost any situation
you're put in from a technical
perspective
yeah yeah huge thing yeah yeah and it
was that's uh
Yahoo that I really first came across
hacker one as well so
that was that was my real pivot into
into bug Bounty was was through Yahoo
um and I did everything I could to get
on the on the team that was helping out
with
um assessing impact of bugs that come in
through the Yahoo program
and that's where
started to learn some of the uh some of
the bigger names on on the Yahoo
programs
um and kind of seeing some of the stuff
they were doing was like I could do this
yeah yeah this this is starting to is
starting to click so so you you then
pivoted you know I guess maybe you were
still on the internal red team but you
also did some work with the bug Bounty
program for Yahoo and that's how you got
exposed to hacker one
yep yeah gotcha and then yeah next in
your in your flow was that you actually
went and worked with hacker one for a
little bit right so how did that come
about yeah definitely
um as with most uh kind of job moves in
this industry I was in Vegas and
um a good friend uh
took us out for uh for a nice
meal and um just had a bit of a chat
with him afterwards saying hey this is
this like on thing sounds quite
interesting and uh
I think uh it kind of snowballed from
there and
I was uh was offered a job relatively
shortly after um
after that and um
Went to went went to work for a for hack
on in London it was a kind of technical
program manager
uh
and how did you like that in comparison
to like because leading up to this
you've basically been doing purely
technical roles like lots of pen testing
lots of red teaming lots of writing
reports that kind of stuff and then you
pivoted from that into like a technical
adjacent role where you're managing
programs you're still very involved with
like security and that kind of stuff
right but but it's a very different
experience what was that like
uh it was challenging it was um I knew
hacker one was a company but I wanted to
be involved with
um
but it was a difficult role for me it
was a difficult week
um
and then unfortunately had some kind of
my personal life ticket took a bit of a
turn and uh that made that may work very
very difficult
um so during my time at hacker one
um my wife and I found out we were
pregnant
um but unfortunately very soon after we
found out that the uh the baby
um had Edward's syndrome which is kind
of chromosomal disorder which meant they
weren't weren't going to make it that's
terrible I'm sorry to hear that
So that obviously took quite a lot of my
uh my attention away from my job and uh
hack them on fantastic throughout the
whole thing and then um when it came to
when the but it was born
I was given kind of three months paid
Improvement leave and uh
went back to I think I went into the
office on the uh January the 3rd 2019
and quit because I just couldn't do it
um
during that leave Did you sort of like
step back and re-analyze like where your
job was at and how you were feeling
about working and all that kind of stuff
or did that kind of all hit on on the
day you went back into the office yeah
yeah kind of they went back into the
office it was
um it was the kind of period where I was
off was very much about self-care and
looking after my wife and family
um and I realized I just wasn't wasn't
ready to to go back to work
um and I didn't want to put a heck of
one in a position of
having somebody on salary who wasn't
doing any work so um
I kind of spoke to my team there and
said
really appreciate everything but uh I'm
just gonna step back so was that day one
of full-time bug bunny after that
uh not day one that took a few months a
few more months and then kind of
realized I do need to start earning
money and that's where I thought yeah I
should
hmm
come pull my finger out and get starting
so I think it was like April yeah
actually I think it comes up coincided
with the UK tax year so April 6th or
something I was like right
let's do this give this a go and see
what we get
um so you're you've been your transition
into uh your transition into bug Bounty
was
a little bit they're a full-time bug
Bounty was
a little bit more strained than most
people's I think that you know we've
kind of talked in the past before about
being in a full-time bug Bounty position
and and um and the kind of mental stress
that that puts on somebody
um and normally I think you and I both
agree that it's not prudent to go into
that position without you know a decent
Financial Runway and a decent
um or at least from our my conversation
uh you know a decent home life setup and
stuff like that
um but that that that transition
actually happened a little bit different
for you so did
um you know what were the first couple
months obviously you were dealing with a
lot of personal things as well but from
a work perspective
um did you did you find it hard to to
focus or or were you kind of ready to
get back into it after having taken an
appropriate amount of time to you know
grieve and such even though that you
know an appropriate amount can never be
be taken enough for you to to get back
into it
yes so it was I mean
I've been working with security as I say
for
would have been 12 years or something by
that point
um so
security is a relatively well paid
industry so I I did have the financial
backing to um so you have to do it
without risk and my wife was going back
to work around the same time as well and
she's a Management Consultant so again a
relatively well paid um
uh job there so with the two incomes
that's good and the money we had in the
bank it was wasn't as much of a of a
risk sure
I I think I said to myself I'll give it
three months before I reassess see see
how we get on
um and if I need to get another job at
the end of that then I would start to
look but um
that was four and a half years
so had you been thinking about doing
full-time bug Bounty or anything prior
to that or was it kind of just like in
the in that time of your life you were
just analyzing sort of the available
options things that you've been doing
and it was kind of a logical step to
just give it a shot and see what happens
or had you kind of been toying with that
in the back your mind that you know I I
like bug Bounty I'm very involved in bug
Bounty obviously working at hacker one
and doing Yahoo bug bending program
before that you're you know very in the
scene you're very in the know your your
mind is kind of in the right place and
whether kind of just like that natural
progression or or was this something
that had always been in the back of your
mind for
you know for a while yeah so I whilst
working at hacker when I was still
hacking on obviously on programs that I
wasn't managing um
and I'm always using that as my kind of
technical Outlet whilst doing less
technical work um at hacker one
um I think without it's not difficult to
say without
how how things could have been different
um
I I very much believe in hackeron and
their kind of vision so I could see that
I would have stayed with them
um whilst keeping on hacking in the in
the background
um but difficult to say
um
did you experience a lot of challenges
with that balance of like TPM and hacker
because I've heard a lot of on both
sides of it of like
you know whether it's being a triage or
whether it's working adjacent to triage
or doing TPM or whatever at hacker one
and also trying to do that the hacking
and you mentioned that there are certain
programs you can't hack on and that kind
of stuff did you find that to be a real
big hindrance that made you excited to
no longer be working there or was it
kind of just like you know if you were
still working there that's fine you
could have gotten around it and and
figured out how to hack outside of it
yeah I don't think it was too much of
hindrance
um I wasn't working on any of the
I think there was only one or two
programs that I was working on that I
personally would have had a huge amount
of interest in hacking uh and there are
obviously a lot of programs available so
I don't think it would have been too bad
the bigger thing would have been the the
time and the um and the energy it's
obviously working for
was primarily an American company
um on UK hours you kind of have to be a
lot more flexible with your with your
time to fit in meetings with with the
states
um certainly West Coast
um
so kind of end up working later in the
evenings which is where at the time I
would have been hacking so uh for
example it's 9 30. it's 9 30 a.m here in
California yeah I imagine it's probably
five or six p.m in the UK
yes yeah half five so yeah
half five what does that mean is that 5
30.
this is a top five Yeah by this point
that's one of my favorite YouTubers
because it's for Americans it's
extremely ambiguous as to what that
means meanwhile we say like Corner yeah
quarter after
yeah yeah and uh in Europe as well in
German it would be uh half six because I
do half two and we do half pass away
really yeah oh no that's that's the
worst
um
wow so so you know bring it back to you
know this new this new stage of life
you're in with with full-time bug Bounty
you've been I started in March of 2020
full-time bike bounty and you started in
April of 2019 so you've got a year a
year on me and there there are very few
people I'll say that have been able to
um sustain
long-term full-time bug Bounty Yasin has
done a great job of it you've done a
good job of it
um you know people but people often have
a hard time with burnout and with um I
guess just the mental stress that comes
along with it even though their earnings
might be might be good
um so do you have any tips or tricks for
people that are looking to get into
full-time bug Bounty and how to
um survive the the mental tolls of that
yeah I mean the first one is
get your finances in order yeah um I
have a lot of people who've come to me
and speak to me about full-time work
hunting I think I wrote something on it
in 2020 maybe
um
and off the back of that I've had a lot
of conversations but it's always make
sure your finances in order is the first
thing
um it was a very low risk
move for me because my previous
experience and connections I was pretty
certain I could get a job quickly if I
needed to
um
I also have the I'd say over a decade of
technical professional experience in
security
so I knew what I was doing
and familiarity with hacker one and some
other
um workbench programs so
for people who want to get into it first
thing is just minimize your risk make
sure you've got enough money in the bank
if you've got a bad run of things that
could be easily three months easily have
a bad run of things
um
so if you're
bug hunting to pay your next rent bill
that's that's not a good position to be
in
um
and then on the kind of burnout side of
things for me personally I work well
when I am working I'm just ramping back
up again now
um I work about three days a week um
and I'm relatively strict with that
because I
um do Child Care the other we have a
couple of days
um while my wife works and that gives me
a lot of time away from the computer so
with my family with my kids
um which which certainly helps
and I try to only hack on programs that
I enjoy
I know
I could make more money if I were to
hack on things that didn't interest me
but I'm disciplined enough to say I want
I want to do this and I want to feel the
joy of
of doing this
um if I sit down at my
on my computer and Dread what I'm doing
that day that's not where I want to be
and that's
one of the big reasons I've not look to
go back into full-time work is I enjoy
what I do when I set the
I set the direction for what I do on a
daily basis and in and on the long term
as well
um giving somebody else that power again
I would find very difficult yeah no
absolutely and I I think that's
something that yeah I I'm beginning to
learn for myself now as well is like
even though I have the freedom to work
Less hours and and you know certainly I
do take more time off than I would be
allowed if I were working you know in in
an industry you know if I had a
traditional job
but um the ability to say all right I'm
actually going to work four days a week
or I'm going to work three days a week
is something that as weird as it sounds
I haven't really considered up until
this point
um especially with the other Ventures
that I have going on it sometimes it
works out that way but you know it's
four days of hacking one day of real
estate you know three days of hacking
one day of training one day of real
estate or whatever right and so I think
that's something that going into this
next phase for me um in 2024 I kind of
want to set the goal of trying to cut my
work hours down to you know
um to four days a week or maybe even
three uh under your under your uh
example here
um and I think that will actually help a
lot with with lifestyle balance because
it is really easy to to get hyper
focused on bug Bounty and to
um you know burn out on it really
quickly so yeah that that aspect of
taking a break and and having that built
into your schedule
um I think is very powerful
yeah it's that and it's the flexibility
as well so if you're having a bad day
just being able to say no I'm done yeah
just just walking away I I'm stubborn as
[__] about that you know like if I'm
having a bad day I'm like no the bad
days are where you know your true
character is defined you know and and I
just try to push through it and my wife
is like you idiot like if you're having
a bad day and you have the total
flexibility to take it off why would you
work in an environment where you're like
unhappy uninterested burnout like why
would you do that like this is in a
terribly inefficient and she's so right
um and so that's such a great lesson and
I'm glad to see that that's been
producing you know results for you as
well
yeah no certainly the flexibility is
but that's something that I I really
value so I can work normal working hours
or I can work kind of 10 p.m through to
3 A.M if you need to or just take a day
off and work on it on the weekend when
everybody else is taking a day off so
you get to do everything that's
so if you want to go do something do it
on a Wednesday because nobody goes out
on Wednesdays right and right yeah then
just work on a Saturday we'll see that
to compete with other people that's the
other great thing man especially for
people that like to travel is like you
can make that happen in the middle of
the week right especially especially if
your partner can make it happen as well
it's so awesome to be able to just like
show up to these sightseeing places and
there's no one there you know at you
know 2 p.m on a Tuesday you know
um and so yeah what a what a great
benefit that is as well yeah um sorry
yeah go ahead I walked out of the room
but I wanted to ask so when you do work
like three three days a week or
something do you find that your workload
sort of compensates back for a five day
work week so say you're working for 40
hours a week eight hours a day five days
a week
um do you find that you're working like
12 13 14 hours on those three days
uh I wish I could sometimes but no
because because you've got the uh I've
got young kids it's very much
some days it will be at one one PM my
wife needs to be online to do work
so that's my hard deadline I'll take
that get the kids go down the park and
and that that's it me be done for that I
can pick it up maybe when they go to bed
if there's something I'm right in the
middle of but um
it is relatively strict to three days a
week unless I want to kind of stay up
late uh in evenings and some evenings
they will do that nice how do you how do
you organize really into it
how do you organize when you have like
you know you're like working four hours
dip for three hours come back work for
three hours leave hacker to a dude that
was my next question no it's how do you
how do you do that yeah
badly I think
[Music]
I'm I'm getting better at note taking
um and that's that's kind of been a big
push this past
the past couple years
um so I keep everything in gitlab so use
oh actually use project tissue tracking
for kind of leads potential bugs things
I want to look at
and have it all all in there I'll write
my whole reports in uh in there and sign
them off and then copy them into
into the platform
um and I found that works quite well
because it also lets me
if I am away from the laptop and I have
a really good idea I can just jump on to
gitlab open a new issue or append a
comment to an issue that I'm working on
um and that's been working relatively
well
um I've let it lapse a little bit
recently because I haven't been working
so much
um but I need to get back into that kind
of discipline nice that's such a
developer-centric approach I love that I
think it's a it's funny because
generally like I think a lot of
developers but myself especially I'm
very like in favor of running it
yourself and like doing all that kind of
stuff but this is one of those cases
where a cloud service or any type of
like hosted
whatever is so so useful because I did
the same thing with like notion for my
that's what I use for my notes where if
I have something come up and I just am
out on the street or I'm traveling or
whatever and I just think of something I
can pull my phone out I can open the app
I can jot it down in notes and then
later when I'm in a position to be
hacking I can open up my notion and I
can go through and I can see the notes
that I left for myself and it's so so
useful to have just that instant being
able to just write it down and then
access it later where you know if you
you're hosting it yourself you might be
able to do that but it's it's a lot more
difficult and there's more Loops you got
to jump jump through and all that kind
of stuff
yeah you know what's kind of odd to me
is that it a lot of the things that
you're talking about
they're they seem really developery for
lack of a better word but you've never
been a developer is that is that
accurate not professionally no yeah so
your whole your whole career has been
um you know uh security
um but there are a lot of a lot of
correlations which I think is is very
interesting and it's probably uh sort of
a I imagine is a mindset
um just sort of base for you
um as far as that goes
yeah and it's a discipline thing as well
I have the worst memory in the world so
if I don't write it down I'll remember
it in like six days time when it's not
used to me um
so I I do have to do that and it I also
find it fun
um
if I don't write it down I'll hyper
fixate on it as well yeah so if I write
it down I can put it put it to one side
and focus on what I'm doing yeah
um I've joked a couple of times in the
past that I've found more bugs whilst
lying awake in bed than I do at the at
the computer yeah
um but if I don't write it down at that
point I just won't sleep because yeah
it's not open up that's that's I think
that's a great tip for anyone who needs
to have a work-life balance with book
Bounty you know if you're if you're a
single guy and you're just like really
just trying to like freaking love the
bug Bounty and I remember sitting you
know before I was married and doing some
hacking and I would just hack for a
super long Sprints and I was just always
in the zone and the flow go go go but as
as I've you know realized the importance
of work-life balance and and you know
maintaining my other relationships
um the ability to step away from the
computer and not lose a bunch of
um you know obviously you're going to
lose your mental contacts for sure but
if before you can do that if you can
predict by you know setting a timer
whatever you know for five minutes or
ten minutes before you have to leave
writing down where you're at currently
and then being able to come back to that
I found it's a lot easier to get back in
that flow State when you return to it uh
and and it seems like that's what what
you've been thinking as well with with
sort of trying to get back into taking
notes yeah hugely
um kind of my my next step in
progression on that this next year is to
really flesh out methodologies for
myself
um so I
a lot of my bug hunting sorry either
very ad hoc or I get a particular
I find a particular type of bug and then
look around for that book on different
programs
um
I'm just I'm not a very good
like if you're simply down in front of
Weber I'll get broader than three
seconds
um
but if I've got a methodology I know I
can follow and and that can help me pick
out interesting things to look at
um I think that will really help me and
then if I get some source code
um rather than just looking for I again
I hyper fixate on code execution
um because that's the real big big bug
but there are
hundreds of bugs I don't even bother
looking for which are really big impacts
so yeah
I'm gonna
my goal for kind of 23 24 is from train
myself and and really
um formalize a lot of things that I'm
doing so that's that's a great segue
right into your your
um you know bug bounty hunting
methodology Joel did you have something
you wanted to add before we moved to
that I was just gonna say that that's
something that happens I think I I
certainly experienced it a lot where
it's like the things that I look for is
like a sliding window where over time as
I find new stuff that I find really
interesting or new techniques or
whatever like that's what I'm really
looking for like when I'm present and
hacking and things that I would look for
even like six months ago or a year ago
are just not as interesting or not as
important or not really what like I
might look for it if I happen to see
something and be like oh yeah let me
check for that but oftentimes I'll be
pivoting into like different
exploitation techniques a specifically
and and exclusively as I as I progress
and I'll just like kind of shift the
things that I look for over time instead
of looking at every single thing that
I've ever looked at ever in my entire
history of hacking
um do you how do you like manage that do
you keep like notes of you know
different categories or um there's a
site we've talked about hack tricks
that's kind of like this where there's
different categories for like xss what
you could do in XYZ scenario like do you
have anything like that
uh I have in the past
um and I've lost several versions of it
um I am trying to build it up again for
again it's for folks that interest me
and that that's the key thing I I never
want to be looking for every bug because
that's going back toward it and that's
not what interests me
um but I personally find xss really
quite quite boring to look for the only
time I ever look for it is if I need an
exercise to trigger an RCA or something
like that right
um actually I was talking to somebody
the other day so I've I've only found
one signal injection bug in my bug
Bounty career
and I was using that to trigger another
more uh better bug and um that's great I
love that yeah they're just not bugs
that interest me because the fix is
input validation or output encoding and
it's just not an interesting thing yeah
that's awesome so it sounds like
generally
nice yeah so when you're hacking like
you're not looking at the mediums and
that stuff like what what are you
generally submitting is it pretty much
highs and crits and very selective like
I think like Justin and I have a
slightly different methodology on this
generally like I'm very pick and choose
about what I want to submit I only
really want to submit like super high
quality super high impact as higher
critics I can get type vulnerabilities
and Justin views it more as like uh
volume is also important especially when
you do it full time and so having a flow
of mediums maybe not lows but mediums
especially is like really important to
keep a regular flow of income and then
working on those highs and crits is also
obviously important just for big bonuses
and all that kind of stuff
dude I'll I'll report it low I don't I
don't give a [__]
I guess
just just just yeah sorry yeah continue
Alex sorry
um yeah so I definitely uh aim for the
hives and the Grits
um I think my my target is kind of
around one or two
um a month
um on kind of bigger paying programs and
that normally Tides me over
um I was yeah I was looking at I wrote
this down somewhere in four and a half
years I've submitted under 200 books
um
yeah
so I I do go for
very much for fewer and higher impact
issues where I can
um that kind of changes a little bit if
we're talking about life hacking events
and then pretty much medium Plus or
we'll go for those yeah
um again I I don't like taking the time
to report those I I often find reporting
low issues is
detrimental to
spending the time on finding other
issues so yeah
yeah
I just ran the numbers on that it's it's
uh that's for that's for vulnerabilities
per month on average it seems which is
pretty for a full-time hunter that
that's yeah that is for that impact is
just high quality you've got to be
pushing out yeah
yeah so on the topic of Elections and
titles that change like your hacking
flow do you
um do you pretty much only do live
hacking event prep or how much are you
doing
typical standard program hacking versus
jumping to lhes
um
so I kind of have a a kind of All or
Nothing on lifelike events and that's um
not just effort that's performance as
well
um I've bond in so many live hacking
events like only being able to report
kind of one or two Mega bugs and I feel
kind of feel like um necessity at that
time all I get
one or two or three really high impact
books right right
um and that so my normal focus is kind
of there but it's a bit more muted if I
can get one really high impact bug in
the Life hacking event I'm happy
um
and then I'll work around uh work around
that
um and again that also depends on who's
running it as well if I'm really engaged
with the with the customer and I think
Justin mentioned earlier uh GitHub was a
good example of that last year as soon
as they were announced as the customer
as soon as they are announced as the
customer I went all in on GitHub
so the normal life hacking event period
is about two weeks of hacking once you
know the full scope of what I think
event but as soon as the customer was
announced it's all right okay
all in so I think I had about four and a
half nearly five weeks of hacking on
them and that paid off
hugely
um
yeah that's that's awesome man and and
yeah I I remember the Majesty of that
that performance uh that will always be
concreted in my mind uh as one of the
greatest live hacking event performances
I've ever seen so congrats on that and
in in conjunction with that I wanna I
wanna talk a little bit about
um your your bug hunting techniques uh
but also you know let's look at
specifically for live hacking events so
you know you mentioned that you're
focusing on high in critical bugs and on
in life hacking events you don't get to
pick your target right which I I
understand you're normally pretty picky
about because you have a specific set of
um
of a very particular set of skills uh
that I was gonna say if you want yeah
exactly that you that you are going to
use to to hunt down the the high in
critical bugs um but that apply less
well to other areas just by nature of of
how that is so
um when you're going can you explain to
me a little bit about what kind of areas
you're looking at uh if there's any
indicators to you of what might be
interesting for these higher and
critical bugs because a lot of people
are stuck in the area where they they're
finding you know mediums lows and the
occasional high but the crit is very
Elusive and you're one of the people
that consistently finds crits um so
could you talk a little bit about that
yes so I mean the first thing I'll look
for is any kind of source code or
desktop application that's in scope
um or where I think I mentioned earlier
where they're using kind of Open Source
modules that that I can access the
source on
um
that's my my comfort zone
um so as soon as I see something like
that I'll I'll dive into it head first
normally if you see a desktop
application Escape Bounty program it'll
be a
electron or chrome chrome embedded
framework applications so you can pretty
much get the source out of them easily
as well to go through
um
and then it's anything that kind of hits
my
uh I guess bloody sense of where an
issue is so any PDF rendering any HTML
rendering
um I'll always spend time there so I had
a very productive kind of six months in
the last year
um looking at headless browser
exploitation
um
so that was
kind of kicked off with h1702 last year
I think yeah in Vegas
uh yes it was that was uh one target I
was looking at that that had um was
using headless Chrome to uh to render
some some attitude it wasn't using but
this this is one case where I did have
to find a cross-site scripting um
but I saw they were using an old version
so it was like huh
I do wonder if I could write an expert
for that well not not ruin one for
Chrome before but let's see what I can
do so why not try and write a chrome
exploit under pressure in a few days
because because that sounds like fun
right
but I I was lucky enough there was
enough information out there on this
older version
um at the time to to Cobble something
together
um and did very well with that book
um yeah and that kind of gave me the
well for that sort of I I was gonna say
you know on on that note I'm sorry to
interrupt um but you know at that time
that was really that was something
really impressive that we had that not a
lot of us had seen uh at the boatmany
scene because you know you do see a lot
of this stuff in sort of more of the
Pontoon or like just actual just people
that hunt for zero days uh and don't do
the competitions
um you know you've seen those there but
that that sort of browser exploitation
wasn't something we had done had seen a
lot of in the book Bounty scene before
so could you talk to me a little bit
about how
you you went on that path of being of
learning about browser exploitation and
um how you did it so quickly to be able
to write an exploit uh for this specific
Target in in a couple days that seems
like Quite a feat
yeah so um
modest experience with blender
exploitation anyway so I kind of
understand all the um
the principles of of what you need to do
so bypassing aslr
what to do when you've got control of
the programming counter and all the rest
of it I kind of get those fundamentals
but um I hadn't looked at a full-on
browser
um JavaScript exploit before the
GitHub security blog had some really
good
um posts on it about exporting very
similar issues than the one I was trying
to do
um so I started reading up there I
can't remember the person's name who's
writing these books and probably butcher
it if I did try to try to say a really
detailed exploitation um
kind of exploitation steps of how they
went about finding and exploiting some
books so that was a really good stepping
stone
um to help me with that
and it was from that point on when when
I knew it was possible it was just sheer
force of will and and no sleep I think
of that well okay so that's I'm glad you
added that last bit because I was like
in those situations when I when I get in
that situation when I lock on I'm like I
know this is possible I gotta get it
done right then that's when the rubber
hits the road for that life balance
stuff that I preach about all the time
right yeah that's when I say like all
right am I gonna just brain dump onto
this notepad and then go to bed at a
decent time with my wife or am I gonna
you know sit here and write code till
3am in the morning and and so I mean
I guess no I'm gonna put you on the spot
like what what happened that that during
that event I mean what what did that
that life balance look like for you
um it was relatively good at the start
of the event because I had no bugs and I
didn't have any leads
it was about halfway halfway through the
event that came across this Target and
uh and realized it was going to be
vulnerable and that's where it did
kind of take over a bit yeah but then
you'd also have the
um kind of difference in that your
flying away from your family or or your
usual um
routine so going out to Vegas I had
eight hours on a flight and a laptop
again so it's like right okay let's see
what I can do there I think by the time
I landed I had most
Primitives in place that I needed to be
able to prove it was vulnerable yeah and
then from that point on it was then
trying to write a reliable exploit for
the particular version in use
and really hammering that home I
remember I think I got it at about
um
5 a.m Vegas time I I finally popped it
on the day of the it was either the day
before or the day of that particular
customer uh
yeah so was it a full exploit to rce or
was it just like a POC where it crashes
or something
uh it's a Phil expert to RCA
um but with without a Sandbox let's go
Okay so
a lot a large portion of the time when
you see headless browsers being used
um in a back end
the sandbox will have been disabled
because it's easier to deploy that way
um and that makes exporting it so much
easier I've only done one successful
full renderer rce through sandbox escape
and that was
fun I'm not interested in doing that
again yeah so I am curious like do you
think it's worth it taking that last
like couple inches because I I've
reported something very similar we got
paid for it at a live hacking event
um I think you'd say it was it was meta
it was a hardware device and it was
using an outdated Chromium browser
essentially and so what we did was we
found a POC for
that same version range and it was able
to successfully crash it but we didn't
decide that it was really worth the
effort to like push it just that last
couple inches to go from Crash
definitely valid like you could take
this further to all the way to like full
Roc rce POS POC do you think that it's
worth it to do that or will the company
kind of understand and this is kind of
company by company but generally do you
think it's it's worth it to like spend
all that time and effort developing a
full working POC or is it good enough to
say here's a CBE for the V8 engine it
applies to this version we can see that
it crashes with this POC
you can connect the dots
um
in my experience
every time I haven't had a full RC PSE
I've been like it's been downgraded to a
medium or [__] off
um
the recent live hacking event I I had
one with a I just submitted POC I was
like this would be a hercu laying effort
to get to rce and they were like yeah
here's two hundred dollars
yeah so oh my gosh the the benefit and
this is what I really found last year
was that once I had one
and people learned that I had one they
would come to me and say
oh I've got this one over here have you
gone Expo for that and if I didn't but I
thought there was one that I could again
develop I would go when I did would do
that sort of thing in the end last year
I wrote three a full Chrome render rces
um
a phantom Js
RCA and a WK HTML to pdfrc
um and each one of those got used at
least twice
um wow in in collabs as well which kind
of really helped because once it's there
it's no effort for me to say or very
little if I change the version numbers
and some offsets right wow so this is
this is sort of like the the reverse
today is new is like you know you go to
today's new when you need a sub domain
takeover an access on a subdomain or
like you know like some sort of cookie
inject you know or it's some some lower
level bugs that will help you build a
greater chain and you go to Alex Chapman
when you need a crazy you know super
exploit for your you know uh
vulnerable-ish looking uh browser
renderer that's happening that's that's
really cool because that model really
does that model really does work we've
seen it time and time again uh at one of
the last live hacking events Eric took
first place without having a single
report that was his own it was all
collaboration
which was just
absolutely legendary and made bug Bounty
history about what the power of
collaboration you know has
um
so it's cool to see the flip side of
that as well with you
um and and I think that speaks to uh
your your experience within
collaboration as well because you you
collaborate a lot with a specific set of
people at live hacking events and I'm
sure that helps the scenarios where
um you know you like you mentioned your
your buck bounding experience is kind of
up and down like that
um so could you talk a little bit about
that collaboration experience and how
it's helped you uh grow as a hunter and
also as it's helped your performance in
life hacking events
yeah I mean it's
collaborating in life hacking events is
always a lot more fun than doing it on
your own anyway yeah
um and that that's kind of the
one of the things I always call back on
I enjoy my job and I want to enjoy my
job
um so it's fun to just get get together
with the group friends and and go at it
but also the
uh the hacking so I've been working with
um on a few events so Archangel rezo and
DC
um they all have different areas of
interest and
um and focus than me so
if I fail to get my one critical then
they've between them they've got 50 or
60 reports and
um that we can uh
that we can profit through
um but if I get my one big bug then
it goes goes the other way so it's it's
been a really good good way of working
for me recently
um certainly a life hacking events and I
bet that helps as well with your growth
as as a hacker when it comes to like
being able to see
other hackers in their style as well
because you mentioned before that you're
you're not as strong in the traditional
web vulnerabilities
and having someone like you know
Archangel and and rezo people that have
strong web backgrounds
um and then having access to those
reports as well is I'm sure just a great
learning opportunity and then vice versa
for them being able to see your your
deeply technical source code powered
um you know Mega crits uh I'm sure helps
them grow as well
yeah and that that's
kind of part of the thing as well if
you're not if you're not learning or
doing bug Bounty you're doing something
wrong it's um
you can always want to be trying to
improve yourself and and your skill sets
and um collaboration is one of the
easiest ways to to Kickstart that
yeah yeah that's really interesting um
so for like
the binary exploitation side versus
source code review do you find that
you're doing a lot more of the binary
exploitation or what do what kind of
stuff are you really focusing on now
um
I do less binary exploitation
than I that want it's always a lot more
involved and it's got a lot higher costs
to to doing it
so
whilst I would love to
have that be my main area of focus one I
don't think I'm skilled enough in there
in it and two
it's not as reliable income as source
code review and other forms of testing
so
if it was just down to me every other
week I'd be doing binary exploitation
and filling in other areas in between
but um
I'm not quite their skill level yet I
don't think so we've talked about this a
little bit when we talked about source
code review we had a whole episode about
it but do you when you do your source
code review is it more of like a sort of
outside in approach or an inside out
approach meeting do you find interesting
like sinks like uh you know there's a
command being run here or do you say
here's a public endpoint that looks like
it it might have juicy functionality let
me see how I can connect these two
together
um how do you how do you sort of
approach a code base when you're looking
for those really high criticality
vulnerabilities
yeah so I tend to focus on the sinks and
then and then work backwards from there
so as I said I kind of hyper focus on
code execution wherever I can
and be that through uh command injection
deserialization
[Music]
um writing arbitrary files that sort of
thing that's
that always kind of Peaks my interest in
um
and that's where I spend my my time
um I over focus in those areas
so I know I could be finding a lot more
bugs if I if I looks a bit more
generally and again that's kind of one
of my um goals for this this next year
or two
but also to bring in more automation
into my kind of source code review and
binary reverse engineering so I've been
playing around with uh code QR semi uh
yearn and a few others um
to uh kind of help with that and build
up a methodology there yeah where do you
draw the line that's a
good sorry there's a crazy audio delay
so it's like we keep talking over each
other where do you like draw the line in
terms of when you're when you're going
sort of inside out right like if you
have a something that looks like code
execution and you've flushed out sort of
what you think are all the paths
do you there's always kind of that
possibility that you might be
misunderstanding something or there
might be a connection somewhere else
where do you draw that line and say okay
it's time to move on and look at the
next sync
um
normally based on my frustration level
if I feel that I've been hammering on it
yeah if I've been hammering on it for a
couple of days
and really can't just can't see any
any future in it then I'll I'll try
something else and probably I'll
probably go back to it for a couple of
days later on so take a break go back to
it
um
and then sometimes I'll just outright
think no no where that's going to be
exploitable and then somebody like vax
will come along and exploit the exact
same thing that I was looking at I hate
that man I freaking hate it when vax
does that he he did it on one of the
gitlab bugs
um
exif tool
I checked the logs um I was looking at
it about two weeks before he he
submitted his uh his RC in it I was like
I can see shelling out here but there's
no way to get access to it so I'm just
going to move on and then saw that I was
like oh
man that that that stings and and and I
just want to go back to what you were
saying before um when Joe asked about
sources and sinks uh that we've we've
asked that question a couple times we've
discussed it ourselves as well and I
think this is the first time we've had a
really solid like no I go to sinks you
know a sort of response like um first
and I think that's I think that's really
cool and I think that that shows that
that methodology is absolutely
um you know an appropriate methodology a
methodology that produces really good
results
um and and I think I tend to be on the
on the flip side of that and I like to
try to go look at the sources see where
I can inject you know my input and and
then go down all of the routes you know
and and it may be because I I don't have
as good of a night a perspective on
um
you know which which sinks lead to code
execution like I've recently been
talking about
um configuration file injection and uh
just sort of if you can inject into a
templated uh configuration file right
that there's a lot of chances for for
rce there because
um you know there's this switch of
context between your your current
service and then the service that it's
it's building with that configuration
file yeah
um and so I think maybe as maybe in the
beginning it might be helpful for people
to look at sources and then as they gain
more experience they should look at
syncs would you would you agree with
that
yeah I mean uh
it's really
different different approaches for
different people I I know what I'm
looking for when I'm looking
um at a source repository
um again sometimes to my detriment
because I will I will focus on it
um but I've had two recent examples I've
been doing quite a lot of work on jdbc
um drivers recently
um so looking at what can be done with
them and the two jdbc drivers I found
out there that I was able to find had
archery file read write in
um so that if you you can get this to
connect to a server the sort of just
read anything off your detecting system
or write anything to the connecting
system
um and that was I found most
specifically because I was looking for
the particular file rights
um
and other things and then worked back
from there working at the protocol stack
then being right can I access this yep
okay can I access this yep okay can I
access this yeah okay so if I Implement
a custom diffie-hellman exchange I can
get through to this bit so working
backwards really helps me rather than
working from the input yeah
um I I think this is something that I've
actually seen and this actually goes to
a bug that I want to talk about later
which is our our bug Collision we had at
a live hacking event earlier this year
so forgive me for that
um and we'll get to that but I I want to
I I want to talk about this whole
concept of you know having a protocol
connect and and then have that you know
reverse connection back to the client
have have some have some effect on the
client but I you piqued my interest when
you talked about those connection pieces
so anything uh you know anything you
want to share any little tidbits that
you want to throw out there with regards
to that
I mean yeah generally the security
boundary when a client connects to a
server is less than when a
server connects to it talks back to a
club that makes sense right so there's a
lot of programs assume that
the client will only ever use in an
authorized way um to connect to an
authorized server whereas if you can
um get a client to connect to a server
you control you generally have a much
more privileged
um
access to be able to do to do things and
I'm alluding to the bug that I know
Justin wants to talk about but um
I found that
exact same bug in four or five different
client applications
because the original developers thought
nobody's ever going to stick this on the
server and connect to an untrusted right
so right or stick in the back end
connect on trusted server and then kind
of cloud cicd comes along and Rule using
get an SVN and material and perforce and
and other things to connect to untrusted
service
anything similar with um kind of no code
low code environments okay let's let the
uh the customers connect to their own
databases so here just give us a
database connection string and we'll go
connect your your database and pull the
data from you
um
and the a lot of the clients just
weren't
designed with that security boundary and
yes
yeah so it's really interesting
place to be looking for bugs and again
it kind of fits my if it's a client you
can normally get hold of the software
you can reverse engineer it or look it
up on GitHub so so I'll I'll uh that
definitely is a excellent tip for anyone
looking for high impact bugs there if
there's a database connection that is
being sent from the server to your
database or something of the like great
stuff there but I wanna I wanna go back
to that jdbc piece that you said you
know uh so let's say I've got a jdbc
configuration uh injection right where I
where I can have it connecting out to my
DV
um you know I'm not gonna I'm not gonna
prevent you from sharing your your
research here but uh any any specific
directions you want to point us in or
are are we looking for a blog post in
the future or is this gonna we're
keeping our cards close to our chest on
this one yeah I mean I'm still actively
exporting a few of these issues okay so
keep a little bit of that well hey the
audience can't tell me I didn't try
because I tried for you audience so well
I think generally if you can change the
um queer string premises on the jdbc or
if you can control this quiz on the jdpc
connection you can do quite a lot
um a few of the connectors are getting
better so uh I think the
which was it
uh
uh not db2
one of the the not not married lady
might sequel or db2
um namescopes me but they've had two
cities raised against them recently for
this kind of exact same issue and one
was being a specified location the log
file
um through a query string parameter
which meant you could write arbitrary
uh and another one was a gender eye
injection which is similar to the um
bug4j interesting
um exploitation very cool was that was
the word kind of LED you down this whole
Rabbit Hole of looking at jdbc or
uh no I actually picked this up a few
years before that came out and then um
when that came out again it kind of led
me down that path of the path again so
um nice
yeah he was in early and early uh early
yeah
yeah if it had like 4J that would have
been uh that would have been a good
thing yeah a lot of your misses here
Alex like come on man I need to start
hanging around Alex
um just everything that Alex was now I'm
gonna write that down
yeah write that down right away
um uh so I think uh we're running to a
close here on on time but um I did want
to talk about uh this this this bug and
I think uh it's enough in the past now
that we can kind of
um that we can kind of talk about it a
little bit uh this this was a bug at a
live hacking event
um earlier this year and it was a rce
that and this is the thing that makes me
sad too is that um this is a blog post
that Alex wrote up on a specific
vulnerability in a specific protocol uh
per force and um and I you know using to
be fair to myself using other resources
and Alex's Vlog
um I found uh you know an rce on this on
this target the share Target that we had
and um and then uh I submitted the
report before Alex did
so
and we split the Bounty right because
it's a live hacking event dupe but um uh
you know it was one it was a really
um great example of the way that Alex
Alex thinks and and what we were talking
about earlier with blogging about things
that you're passionate about
um and a perfect example of this client
server trust
um sort of situation that we have
because that's where the phone was
um but and Alex I I don't recall whether
I sent you this specific vulnerability
before we started uh recording the
podcast do you want to talk to the
technical details of this vulner uh did
you do you have the it fresh enough in
your mind or do you want me to take a
stab at it and you can kind of
supplement
yeah I think of um I should be looking
at again recently for something else so
it is
okay all right
man talk us through it this is an
interesting one let's again so for those
who don't know perforce is a version
control system so similar to git or um
SVN that's heavily used in the gaming
industry because it's it works really
well with very large files
um so if you've got really large assets
3D models that sort of thing
um
and it it's a very typical example of
the
the client trust that we mentioned
before so all the um Air Force client
really does is connect to the server and
the server lens says run this command
and then services will say okay show me
what files you've got check the hashes
of the files against the files I've got
so rather than it being client
controlled it's server control
um and that was the first thing that
kind of got my interest I was like well
how does it do how does it give you new
files that you don't have on your system
and it turns out it just sends a uh I
think the command is literally send file
yeah or um or write file client Dash
rate file is what I have in our report
right here which is just gold like I
love that sounds interesting yeah
um
so then seeing that like okay right how
how are we going to go about about
testing this so what do you do break out
Python and then start trying to reverse
engineer the protocol as it's going on
the wire and Wireshark and building up
bite by bite bit by bit
uh to a point where I pretty much had a
fully functioning
um purple server written in Python um
to kind of handle the auth
do all the rest of it to get it to the
point
um where we're just a login it would be
able to write an arbitrary file on the
on the connecting system
and and that was great so then I think
just in saying this this bug collection
Collision on the life hacking event I I
kind of have a bit of a blase attitude
to submitting these books that I don't
think anybody else is going to
submitting by hacking events and this
one I wasn't going to submit in the Duke
period I was like nobody's gonna find
that oh dude that would have been a
nightmare man I'll prove it after the
GPU closes uh because nobody else will
find it and I was like well I've got a
little bit of time I'll get it here holy
moly and then when I found out it's been
Jake was like yeah
yeah right let's as soon as it was due
until I went to the uh tradition I was
like
um can you let me know who who was it
it was it was um and and it was I want
to say on your team as well they took
you guys took bets on who it was right
and and freak who who was it they
guessed it was me one of them correctly
guessed that it was me
I want to say it was Douglas as well
yeah so I appreciated that vote of
confidence it is a uh one of the highest
honors in my bug Bounty career to have
duped and Alex Chapman bug
um so I'm sorry for using your own blog
post against you but
um yeah I've completely forgotten I've
written that to be honest so uh no way
so you didn't even reference back to it
when you when you had oh my gosh
wow that's crazy that's awesome and and
so I just wanted to go to what you were
saying you know you wrote out a full a
full
perforce server and I'm looking at my
exploit right now and uh you know I I
love that experience of writing out you
know like a binary level protocol
um for these sort of things and you know
you said that handles the auth and stuff
like that I'm looking at my code and it
you know handles the authors like yeah
yeah don't mind that you know like it
connects to the server you're like no no
it's fine yes yes you got it correct you
know and then and then you just yeah yes
you're more connected here's the code
run
um and it's just uh it's just a fun
vulnerability type for sure
um so that's awesome
um yeah I think I think Joel I think
Joel has to bounce to a meeting
um so we'll bring it to a close here
um Alex you can for all of you that are
listening you can find Alex on on
Twitter at Ajax Chapman on hacker1 ajx
Chapman uh uh Ajax
chapman.github.com everywhere AJ Chapman
um Alex thanks so much for coming on man
did you have anything that you wanted to
say as we sign off
uh yeah appreciate the uh the work you
guys are doing on the podcast it's uh
it's a good one I've had to stop
listening while I walk the dog works
I've got to fit too many notes
yeah we we get that feedback often
um and so we maybe we need to uh stay on
top of getting our our notes out that
accompany the episodes and uh and
hopefully that'll make for a little bit
more of a leisurely listening experience
yes definitely
um but all right yeah well thanks so
much again with you yeah go ahead Joel
yeah no I appreciate it thanks for
coming on and uh yeah yeah we'll we'll
uh we'll probably be collabing it's at
some point in the future oh yeah we will
cheers
[Music]